Andre Assumpçao

+1 857 200-7739 | andre.assumpcao@gmail.com | https://aasumpcao.github.io/

Summary

Computational social scientist / data scientist / quantitative analyst with expertise in empirical legal studies, political economy of development, and corruption. 10 years of research experience in academia, government, and private sector. Particularly interested in natural language processing (NLP) applications to law, economics, and politics.

Education

The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (UNC Chapel Hill) — Ph.D., M.A. 2015 — 2020

Concentration: Empirical Legal Studies and Political Economy of Development

Getulio Vargas Foundation (FGV) — M.P.P. with honors 2010 — 2012

Concentration: Economics of Corruption; Political Economy; Public Economics

The State University of Campinas (UNICAMP) — B.A. 2004 — 2008

Concentration: Applied Microeconomics

Experience

Post-Doctoral Fellow — UNC's School of Government July 2021 — (current)

1. Currently working on racial equity issues in the U.S. criminal justice system

Senior Researcher — Brazilian Association of Jurimetrics (ABJ) Jan 2021 — (current)

1. Currently working on policy projects to improve the Brazilian justice system and to support the use of empirical evidence in the legal word

Post-Doctoral Fellow — Harvard Kennedy School

- 1. Developed algorithm to process, classify, and extract content from job descriptions.
- 2. Developed algorithm to produce artificial titles for occupations and industries.
- 3. Implemented survey experiments for two applied research projects.

Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant — UNC Chapel Hill

Jul 2015 — May 2020

Jun 2020 — May 2021

- 1. Completed 5+ independent research projects (currently submitted or under review).
- 2. Worked on 5+ advisor-led research projects using experimental research methods.
- 3. Taught independently a graduate-level course on political economy of development and an undergraduate-level course on quantitative analysis of public policy.

Summer Research Intern — The Brookings Institution

Jun 2016 — Aug 2016

- 1. Conducted exploratory data analyses for Metropolitan Policy Program.
- 2. Wrote 5+ analytical pieces for the Paris Global Competitiveness report.
- 3. Wrote independent grant application on the impact of immigration on human capital in U.S. metropolitan areas.

Awards, Funding, and Independent Consulting

Consulting for the Brazilian Office of the Open Knowledge Foundation

Oct 2020 — (current)

Currently applying natural language processing techniques to extract, process, and analyze text of local government gazettes in Brazil. Role also includes creating search engine and data visualization tools in 2021. A sample of the work is available at:

https://github.com/okfn-brasil/querido-diario-toolbox

Won National Award partnering with the Brazilian Association of Jurimetrics (ABJ)

Nov 2020

Working with colleagues at ABJ, won national competition held by the National Council of Justice (CNJ) to structure and analyze court data from all 92 state, federal, labor, military, and electoral courts in Brazil. The winning dashboard is available at: https://github.com/abjur/inovaCNI

Consulted for the Brazilian Association of Investigative Reporting (ABRAJI)

Oct 2019 — Oct 2020

Structured the data feeding ABRAJI's portal containing all lawsuits filed against Brazilian politicians since 2014. Work involved connection to data API, merging court data with various other public data, and text analysis to match plaintiffs and claimants to candidates running for elected office. The portal and underlying code are respectively available at:

https://publique-se.org.br

https://github.com/abraji/publique_se

Institute for Humane Studies Dissertation Funding

2017, 2018, and 2019

UNC Public Policy Summer Fellowship

2018

2017

UNC Graduate School Summer Fellowship

2015 201

Weiss Urban Livability Fellowship, UNC Graduate School

2015 — 2016

UNC Nancy F. Stegman Fellowship

2015

Software

querido-diario-toolbox Python module to perform text extraction, processing, and analysis of local government

gazettes in Brazil.

Python module to perform keyword extraction from any text document using TF-IDF,

WordRank, and Word Embedding methods.

textfind Stata command to do descriptive analysis of keywords in text documents.

<u>emailToEvent</u> AppleScript program to create iCal events from Outlook and Mail in OS devices.

Skills & Abilities

Programming / Markup / Data API Python, R, Stata HTML, CSS, Markdown, Git SQL, Spark, Hadoop (basic) Methods

Causal Inference and Experimental Design Statistical / Machine Learning Natural Language Processing (NLP)